سنكرلي أو سينكو، قرية سورية جميلة جداً تقع شرق ناحية شران،
منطقة عفرين، ريف حلب الشمالي وتتبع لها.
Sankarli or Sinko, a very beautiful Syrian village located
east of Sharran sub-district, Afrin region, in the northern
countryside of Aleppo, and is administratively affiliated
with it.
كما أنها تقع شمال غرب مدينة حلب بـ 55 كيلومتراً، وتبعد عن
مدينة عفرين 15 كيلومتراً باتجاه الشرق.
It is also located 55 kilometers northwest of the city of
Aleppo, and is 15 kilometers away from the city of Afrin
towards the east.
بنيت بيوت القرية بشكل متصاعد فوق سفوح هضبة جبلية متجهة نحو
الجنوب والغرب.
The houses of the village were built in an ascending manner
on the slopes of a mountainous plateau facing south and
west.
سكانها الأصليين من الكرد السوريين، الإيزيديين والمسلمين،
الذين ينتمون إلى قبيلة الشيكاك الكردية، والذين قدموا إليها
من منطقة أورفا بحثاً عن الماء والكلأ.
Its original inhabitants are Syrian Kurds, Yazidis and
Muslims, who belong to the Kurdish Shikak tribe, and who
came to it from the Urfa region in search of water and
pasture.
يعيش في القرية حالياً حوالي 500 عائلة سورية من أهلها الكرد
الأصليين إضافة إلى عوائل مهجرة قسراً من حمص وأرياف إدلب
ومناطق سورية أخرى.
Currently, about 500 Syrian families from its original
Kurdish inhabitants live in the village, in addition to
forcibly displaced families from Homs, the countrysides of
Idlib, and other Syrian areas.
يعتمد أهلها في معيشتهم على الزراعة وخاصة زراعة الزيتون
والكرمة والرمان، وعلى تربية الحيوانات كالأغنام والماعز.
Its people depend on agriculture for their livelihood,
especially the cultivation of olives, vines, and
pomegranates, and on raising animals such as sheep and
goats.
تشتهر القرية بنبعة الماء الموجودة شرقها، وبجب عيسى الموجود
جنوبها.
The village is famous for the water spring located to its
east, and for Jibb Issa located to its south.
ترتفع فيها نسبة الشهادات الجامعية من كافة التخصصات، فيما
توجد فيها مدرسة ابتدائية واحدة، ويتابع الطلاب دراستهم
الإعدادية والثانوية في ناحية شران.
The percentage of university degrees in all specializations
is high there, while it has only one primary school, and
students continue their preparatory and secondary studies in
the Sharran sub-district.
يتميز أهالي القرية بالصدق والطيبة والقساوة في آن واحد، وذلك
بسبب الطبيعة الجغرافية القاسية للقرية.
The people of the village are characterized by honesty,
kindness, and toughness all at once, due to the harsh
geographical nature of the village.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
Peace and the mercy of Allah be upon you.
شلونك عمو؟
How are you, uncle?
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
شلون صحتك؟ عوافي عليك؟
How is your health? Health to you.
وعليكم السلام، أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل تفضل.
Peace be upon you, welcome, come in, come in.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
عبد المنان جاويش من أهالي قرية سنكرلي.
Abdulmannan Chawish, from the people of Sankarli village.
يا أهلا وسهلا فيك عمو.
You are very welcome, uncle.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
واقف عند هالجرن وهالدقماق، إيش عم تتذكر؟ إيش عم تساووا؟
Standing by this mortar and this mallet, what are you
remembering? What are you making?
هذا عم يساووا برغل، بيجيبوا حنطة بكتوا هون، بيسلقوه، بعد
السلق بحطوا هون وبدقوه بهالدقماق لحتى شوي هيك يستوي، يطلع
منه نخالة منه، بعدين بساووا برغل.
They are making bulgur here. They bring wheat and pour it
here, boil it, and after boiling they put it here and pound
it with this mallet until it softens a bit, and the bran
comes out of it, then they make bulgur.
هلق أولي كان بالجرن هذا، هلق صار تطور، سوينا دولاب وحجر أسود
مثل معصرة، عم بيشتغلوا هنيك، يعني تطورت الحكاية.
Now, in the old days it was in this mortar, but now there is
progress, we made a wheel and a black stone like a press,
they work over there, meaning the process has evolved.
هلق هذا كان أولي هيك يستعملوا؟ هيك مو هيك؟
So this is how they used to do it in the past? Like this,
right?
إي، كان اثنين، واحد من هاد الطرف، وواحد من هنيك، واحد يشيل
وواحد ينزل.
Yes, there used to be two people, one on this side, and one
over there, one lifts and one strikes down.
تمام.
Alright.
خلينا نمشي هيك.
Yes indeed.
Let's walk this way.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
هلق هذا الدولاب، إيش قد صار له هالدولاب عم تحكي عليه؟
الطاحون إيه؟
Now this wheel, how old is this wheel you are talking about?
The mill, yes?
حوالي 50 سنة صارت.
It's been about 50 years.
50 سنة؟ ولساته شغال؟
50 years? And it's still working?
لساته شغال بس ما حدا عم بيشتغل عليه، مثل أولي بتقول برغل
وحصاد وشغلات ما في، قليل.
It's still working, but no one is working on it. Unlike the
old days, you know, making bulgur, harvesting, and such
things are no more, it's rare.
صاروا على المطاحن الحديثة.
They switched to modern mills.
على المطاحن، نعم.
To the mills, yes.
طيب، أنت بتتذكر هالأيام هالدولاب؟
Well, do you remember the days of this wheel?
بتذكر إي.
I remember, yes.
كان في غيره هون ولا بس هاد؟
Was there any other one here or just this one?
بس هاد.
Just this one.
يعني يجروه على الحصان ولا؟
So they used to pull it with a horse or what?
يجروه على الحصان هالشكل، على البغل، له خشبة من هون ممدودة
لهون، بيربطوا فيها حصان وبدور حوالي هالعمارة هي لحتى يستوي،
هلق أولي هنيك كان أربع خمس كيلات برغل ينزل فيها، هون حوالي
شوال كانوا عم بينزلوه.
They used to pull it with a horse like this, or a mule. It
has a piece of wood extending from here to here, they tie a
horse to it and it turns around this structure until it's
ready. In the past over there, four or five measures of
bulgur would go into it, but here they would put down about
a sack.
هلق باعتبارك من بيت جاويش، أنا سمعت إنه في شخص يعني اسمه كان
قره حنان، لازم يكون بيقربك؟
Now, since you are from the Chawish family, I heard that
there was a person named Qara Hannan, he must be related to
you?
بيقربني، جدي كان.
He is related to me, he was my grandfather.
جدك، جدك ولا أبوك؟
Your grandfather, your grandfather or your father?
إيوه.
Yes.
شخص يعني بتاريخ سنكرلي كان مهم، تحكي لي عنه شوي؟
He was an important figure in the history of Sankarli, could
you tell me a little about him?
كان مختار الضيعة بوقتها، من حوالي 80 سنة تقريباً.
He was the Mukhtar (village head) of the village at the
time, about 80 years ago.
إيوه.
I see.
إيوه، هو علاقتنا كان مع كلس، هو نائب تقريباً أو محامي بسرايا
كلس، يمشي أمور العالم.
Yes, our relations were with Kilis. He was almost a deputy
or a lawyer in the Kilis seraglio, sorting out people's
affairs.
تمام، معناها أكتر من 100 سنة.
Alright, that means more than 100 years ago.
أكتر إي صار أكتر إي.
More, yes, it has been more than that.
إيش شو كان وضعيته يعني؟ إيش شو إله ميزات؟ إيش شو الشي اللي
بيميزه؟ ليش هو شخصية مهمة؟ شو السبب؟ صاحب حكمة؟ صاحب...؟
What was his status exactly? What qualities did he have?
What distinguished him? Why was he an important figure? What
was the reason? A man of wisdom? A man of...?
من حنكته، من كلامه، من نشاطه يعني، ما بيقصر عن أي شيء يعني.
Because of his shrewdness, his words, his activity, meaning
he never fell short in anything.
كان يمشي مصالح أهل سنكرلي هنيك؟
He used to sort out the interests of the people of Sankarli
there?
بيمشي، سنكرلي وغير سنكرلي.
He sorted them out, for Sankarli and other than Sankarli.
كل القرى اللي هون؟
All the villages here?
نعم.
Yes.
تحفظ لي شي قصة، حافظان شي قصة من هالقصص اللي بتحكي لنا عن
تاريخه؟
Do you remember a story, do you remember any story from
these tales that tells us about his history?
والله حافظانه بس ما... يعني ما...
I swear I remember them but not... I mean not...
يعني أنا سمعت إنه هو كان بحنكته وذكائه ودهائه يحتال على
القضاة لحتى يمشي مصالح أهل بلده؟
I mean, I heard that with his shrewdness, intelligence, and
cunning, he used to trick the judges to get his
townspeople's affairs sorted?
إي قالوا في بوقتها كان في واحد رايح عالجيش وصار له أكتر من
10 أشهر ورجعان إنه مرته ولدانة، قال هالولد مو مني، بدي أروح
أطلق مرتي.
Yes, they said at the time there was a man who went to the
army and was gone for more than 10 months, and he came back
to find his wife had given birth. He said, "This child is
not mine, I will go and divorce my wife."
كويس.
Good.
قاضي حكى معه، قال يا حنان هالشخص هيك هيك شلون بدنا نعمل؟ قال
اتركها علي، صار يمشي بين هالمجتمع، بيقول يا حرام بدهم يعدموا
مرة وزلمة.
The judge spoke with him, he said, "O Hannan, this person is
in this situation, what should we do?" He said, "Leave it to
me." He started walking among the community, saying, "What a
pity, they are going to execute a woman and a man."
إيوه.
I see.
ركضت الزلمة قال خير إن شاء الله لا يكون نحن؟ قال أنتو إيش
مساويين؟ قال والله هيك القصة إنه بدي أطلق مرتي وأنا رحت
عالجيش وضميت 10 أشهر وصار الولد بعد مني.
The man ran to him and said, "I hope everything is alright,
could it be us?" He said, "What have you done?" He replied,
"Well, the story is that I want to divorce my wife because I
went to the army and stayed for 10 months, and the child was
born after I left."
قال مو حرام عليك؟ بس طلع على الولد، عيونه عيونك، ودمه دمك،
شلون بدك تطلق مرتك؟ وبدهم يعدموك إذا ما طلقتها.
He said, "Aren't you ashamed? Just look at the boy, his eyes
are your eyes, and his blood is your blood. How can you
divorce your wife? And they will execute you if you don't
divorce her."
شو؟ لما قالوا أنتو الدم دمك والعيون عيونك، ركضت عليه، كمش
الولد، باسه. يلا قال إلحقوني، راحوا عند القاضي تصالحوا.
What happened? When he told him, "The blood is your blood
and the eyes are your eyes," he ran to her, grabbed the boy,
and kissed him. Then he said, "Follow me," and they went to
the judge and reconciled.
بعدين القاضي قال قره حنان تعال أقعد محلي، أنت لازم تكون
القاضي.
Afterwards, the judge said, "Qara Hannan, come sit in my
place. You should be the judge."
يا حنان تعال اقعد محلي.
"O Hannan, come sit in my place."
إي.
Yes.
الله يعطيك العافية يا عمي.
May God give you health, my uncle.
أهلاً وسهلاً أهلاً.
Welcome, welcome.
الله يكرمك شكراً إلك.
May God honor you, thank you.
الله يحفظك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God protect you, welcome.
من شجرة التوت الخلفي، اللي عمرها يساوي عمر القرية، ومن جب
عيسى اللي صاير بسفح وادي... وادي البير في القرية، ومن زيارة
غريب اللي صايرة في أعلى التلة، تبدأ قصة حكاية قرية سنكرلي.
From the mulberry tree behind me, whose age equals the age
of the village, and from Jibb Issa, which is located on the
slope of the valley... Wadi Al-Bir in the village, and from
the shrine of Gharib, which is located at the top of the
hill, the story of the village of Sankarli begins.
لنحكي عن سنكرلي هالضيعة الحلوة والجميلة، رح يكون معنا العم
رشيد جاويش، أحد أكبر الرجال المعمرين في القرية، والمهتمين
بتاريخها.
To talk about Sankarli, this sweet and beautiful village, we
will be joined by Uncle Rashid Chawish, one of the oldest
men in the village, and one of those interested in its
history.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو دشتي.
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Dashti.
الله يعافيك، يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم أنتو والشباب، أهلاً، بخير
وسلامة جيتوا، شرفتوا، يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God grant you health, you and the young men are very
welcome. Welcome, you came in peace and safety, you've
honored us, you are very welcome.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك. عمي أبو دشتي، احكي لي بداية يعني هالشجرة،
من بداية وجود القرية هون كانت ولا زرعوها أهل القرية قبل
وجودهم؟ كيف الجب شو دوره؟
Welcome to you. Uncle Abu Dashti, tell me first, I mean this
tree, was it here from the beginning of the village's
existence, or did the people of the village plant it before
their existence? What is the role of the well?
حسب اللي شفنا الختيارية اللي قبلنا أكبر منا، الختيارة
والختيار، حكوا إن الجب اللي حافره اسمه عيسى، والشجرة إيمتى
زارعينها، حدا ما، ما بيعرف، ما هو شايف، ما له علم بزرعة
الشجرة.
According to what we saw from the elders before us, who were
older than us, the old women and the old men, they said that
the well was dug by someone named Issa, but as for when the
tree was planted, no one knows, no one has seen it, no one
has knowledge of the tree's planting.
شجرة كبيرة، بيطلع يعني حسب واحد بيطلع عليه 500 سنة، 600 سنة،
ما هو معروف عمرها يعني، ما هو مسجل، ولا في سجل بهيك.
It is a big tree, it seems, I mean according to someone
looking at it, to be 500 years, 600 years old. Its age is
not known, it is not registered, and there is no record of
that.
لكن أنتو اللي سمعتوه من أجدادكم بأنه هم ما بيعرفوا إلا
هالشجرة موجودة؟
But what you heard from your ancestors is that they only
knew this tree as already being here?
إيوه، يعني من زمان موجودة، من زمان حافرين البئر المي، نبع ما
هو جمع، ما هو صهريج، أي خيو أوقات كان بينزل مطر كثير، مي
بيطلع من فوق الجب بيعبي كان.
Yes, meaning it has been here for a long time. The water
well was dug a long time ago. It is a spring, not gathered
water, not a cistern. Oh brother, sometimes it used to rain
a lot, water would come out from the top of the well and
fill it up.
وبيجري بالوادي؟
And it would flow in the valley?
كان بيجري، أنه أوقات وقت اللي بينزل مطر 700 ملم، 800 ملم،
يعني هلق ما بينزل مطر 300 ملم، ما بيسيل.
It used to flow, because sometimes when 700 mm, 800 mm of
rain would fall... Now it doesn't even rain 300 mm, so it
doesn't flow.
تمام. هلق هذا الجب، جب عيسى، كانت كل الضيعة تشرب منه؟
Alright. Now this well, Jibb Issa, did the whole village
drink from it?
كل الضيعة كانت عم تشرب، كان عليها دواب، وتحتها تفيانة
هالشجرة، كان الشيوخ الكبار، ومختار الضيعة، كانوا بيقعدوا،
بيتسلوا، بياكلوا، بيشربوا، هيك عادتنا كان هيك يعني.
The whole village used to drink from it, animals used to
come to it, and under the shade of this tree, the senior
elders and the Mukhtar of the village used to sit,
socialize, eat, and drink. That was our custom, I mean.
وبنفس الوقت النسوان والشباب كانوا يعبوا مي من هون ويسقوا
الحيوانات ويشربوا منها؟
And at the same time, the women and the youth used to fill
water from here, water the animals, and drink from it?
النسوان كانوا بيعبوا، بيسحبوا بالدلو، هي شيء مهم. الدلو
الأولي، اللي بعد ما صارت لاستيك، دلو كان غطاس لاستيك.
The women used to fill water, they would draw it with a
bucket, this is an important point. The old bucket... after
that it became plastic, the bucket became a plastic
submersible.
الدلو الأولي كانوا بيعملوا صليب هيك وجلد، جلد تبع العنز تبع
الخاروف كذا...
The old bucket, they used to make a cross shape like this
and use leather, the skin of a goat or a sheep, and such...
صح.
Right.
وبيدبغوه، بعد الدبغ ويبسوا كانوا بيخيطوا بيربطوا فيه الحبل
وبيسحبوا، أنا شفت بعيني الدلو ما كان لاستيك، كان جلد.
And they would tan it. After tanning and drying it, they
would sew it, tie the rope to it, and draw water. I saw with
my own eyes that the bucket was not plastic, it was leather.
طيب خلينا نمشي هيك شوي على طرف الوادي ونحكي شوي، شرف شرف.
Alright, let's walk a bit this way to the edge of the valley
and talk a little, go ahead, go ahead.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
English Translation
هلق هاد الوادي، هاد الوادي اللي يسمى وادي البير مو هيك؟ أو
وادي...
English Translation
Now this valley, this valley is called Wadi Al-Bir (Valley
of the Well), right? Or the valley...
English Translation
ملقب بوادي البير، معروف بتسأل من واحد عم يقول كلي بيري.
It's nicknamed Wadi Al-Bir, it's well-known, if you ask
anyone they'll say Geliyê Bîrê.
English Translation
كلي بيري، وادي البير.
Geliyê Bîrê, Wadi Al-Bir.
English Translation
تمام. هلق أطراف الوادي، اللي هاد صاير بالطرف الجنوبي للضيعة،
الطرف القبلي... كله فيه مغر.
English Translation
Alright. Now the edges of the valley, which is located on
the southern side of the village, the southern part... it's
all full of caves.
English Translation
من الجانب الشرقي صاير بالطرف الجنوبي، ومن الجانب الغربي صاير
بنص الضيعة.
English Translation
From the eastern side, it's on the southern edge, and from
the western side, it's in the middle of the village.
English Translation
هي مو صاير في كم بيت هون؟
Aren't there a few houses here?
English Translation
إي صاير. الوادي هلق بين الضيعة بيمشي.
Yes, there are. The valley now runs through the village.
English Translation
بيصل لوادي شران؟
Does it reach the valley of Sharran?
English Translation
بيصل لوادي شران.
It reaches the valley of Sharran.
English Translation
أولي كان من الشتي لشهر آب كان العالم عم بيسقي دوابه من مية
هالوادي، كان عم بينزل مي فيها.
English Translation
In the past, from winter until August, people used to water
their livestock from the water of this valley; water used to
flow in it.
English Translation
تحكي لي شقد عمر هالضيعة؟
Can you tell me how old this village is?
English Translation
عمر الضيعة العلم عند رب العالمين، عمر الضيعة حسب اللي يعني
فهمنا من الاختيارية واللي سمعناه...
English Translation
The age of the village is known only to the Lord of the
Worlds. The age of the village, based on what we understood
from the elders and what we heard...
English Translation
يعني أكتر من 500، يعني 500 وهيك، لأنه كان منطقة بوقتها
أحراش، ما كان متل هلق معمر يعني.
English Translation
It's more than 500, like 500 years or so, because at that
time the area was a forest, it wasn't built up like it is
now.
English Translation
وبالنسبة للمغارات فيها الله العليم مين حافر، رب العالمين،
غير رب العالمين ما بيعرف مين حافره، لأنه هالمغارات قديم
خايو.
English Translation
And as for the caves in it, God knows who dug them, the Lord
of the Worlds. No one but the Lord of the Worlds knows who
dug them, because these caves are old, brother.
English Translation
من وين أجو أهلها؟
Where did its people come from?
English Translation
أهلي، أهل الضيعة من وين أجو؟ ما هو مذكور يعني. ما هو مذكور،
ما قالوا إنه جايين من كذا، بس...
English Translation
My people, the people of the village, where did they come
from? It's not mentioned. It's not mentioned, they didn't
say they came from such and such place, but...
English Translation
اسم الشعب اللي ساكن المنطقة عشيرة شكاك.
The name of the people living in the area is the Shikak
tribe.
English Translation
شكاك.
Shikak.
English Translation
إيوا، بواحد بيجوز... ما في هيك شي.
Yes, maybe someone... there's no such thing.
English Translation
حسب ما فهمت إنه أجو من أورفا، لما كانت الحدود مفتوحة. إنه
أجو من أورفا.
English Translation
From what I understand, they came from Urfa when the borders
were open. That they came from Urfa.
English Translation
هي، هي قسم... قسم عشيرة، لواحد جاويش جاي من أورفا.
This, this is a section... a section of the tribe, belonging
to a person named Jawish who came from Urfa.
English Translation
إي في عندك جعفر، في عندك عيسى، في عندك بكر أفندي.
Yes, you have Jaafar, you have Issa, you have Bakr Effendi.
English Translation
يعني فقط بيت جاويش اللي هنن أنتو، جيتو من أورفا.
So only the Jawish family, which is you, came from Urfa.
English Translation
إي جايين من أورفا. بس الجروس اسمها جروس، هيك عم بيقولوا،
هدول كمان من زمان كانوا ساكنين بشران.
English Translation
Yes, we came from Urfa. But the Jerus, their name is Jerus,
that's what they say, they also lived in Sharran a long time
ago.
English Translation
أجو سكنوا هون بيناتنا من زمان خايو ما هو مذكور، وما في أي
يعني... ما هنن عاملين دراسة إنه بأينا عام جايين هين، ما في.
English Translation
They came and lived here among us a long time ago, brother,
it's not mentioned. And there isn't any... they haven't done
a study on what year they came here, there isn't.
English Translation
يعني السكان الأصليين الأوائل اللي أجو لهون هنن أكراد. أكراد
من شكاك، وبيت جاويش، وبيت مين؟
English Translation
So the original first inhabitants who came here are Kurds.
Kurds from Shikak, the Jawish family, and whose family?
English Translation
بيت جعفر، وبيت عيسى، وبيت بكر أفندي.
The Jaafar family, the Issa family, and the Bakr Effendi
family.
English Translation
تمام، تمام. هنن يعني إيزيديين ولا مسلمين؟
Alright, alright. Are they Yazidis or Muslims?
English Translation
أولاً يعني بالحرب العالمية الأولى عم بيقولوا سفر برلك يعني،
خايو كان أكثرية الضيعة إيزيدية.
English Translation
First of all, during the First World War, they say
Seferberlik, brother, the majority of the village was
Yazidi.
English Translation
خايو، بعدين حسب الظروف الاقتصادي والاجتماعي، يعني بعض منهم
اعتنقوا الإسلام.
English Translation
Brother, then depending on the economic and social
circumstances, some of them converted to Islam.
English Translation
بس في شغلة عنا ما بيلتقى بغير منطقة، يا ريت كل جوارينا متل
ضيعتنا يعني. ما في تفرقة بين الإيزيدي وبين المسلم، نحن نشارك
بالأعياد مع بعضنا.
English Translation
But there is something we have that you don't find in other
areas, I wish all our neighbors were like our village. There
is no differentiation between a Yazidi and a Muslim, we
celebrate the holidays together.
English Translation
نحن الإيزيدية نشارك بعيد الصيام، نشارك بعيد الأضحى، مناسبات
الديانة الإسلامية نشارك مع جوارينا.
English Translation
We Yazidis participate in the Fasting Feast, we participate
in Eid al-Adha, we share the occasions of the Islamic
religion with our neighbors.
English Translation
وهنن يشاركونا معنا، بعيد الإيزيدية، بعيد الصيام، بعيد الحج،
بعيد نيسان... بيشاركونا معنا.
English Translation
And they join us too, in the Yazidi holidays, the Fasting
Feast, the Pilgrimage Feast, the Feast of Nisan... they join
us.
English Translation
خايو نحن ما في أي تفرقة دينية أو كره ما في، كل واحد هو
وعمله، بالآخرة الله يحاسب.
English Translation
Brother, we don't have any religious discrimination or
hatred, everyone is responsible for their own deeds, and in
the afterlife, God will judge.
English Translation
في عرب هون؟
Are there Arabs here?
English Translation
أنا إيش عامل، إيش بتعرفني؟ هلق شخصيتي أنا أبو دشتي، بيجوز
إلي أخلاق سرية ما بتعرفها، الله بيعرفها يحاسبني عليها.
English Translation
What have I done, what do you know about me? Now my persona
is Abu Dashti, I might have secret traits you don't know
about, God knows them and will judge me for them.
English Translation
في عرب هون؟
Are there Arabs here?
English Translation
عرب لا ما في. أولي ما كان ولا بيت عربي هون، بالمنطقة ما كان
في.
English Translation
Arabs, no, there aren't. In the past, there wasn't a single
Arab house here, there weren't any in the area.
English Translation
تمام، تمام.
Alright, alright.
English Translation
هلق صاير نازحين، جايين عرب، أتراك، فيها مشكل يعني، نازحين
وين ما كان في.
English Translation
Now there are displaced people, Arabs and Turkmen have come,
it's mixed. There are displaced people everywhere.
English Translation
لاحظت إنه في أشجار توت كتيرة موجودة، الشجرة اللي كنا موجودين
تحتها، وهي الشجرة، وهالمغارات، هي واضحة. شو السبب وجود التوت
هون؟
English Translation
I noticed that there are many mulberry trees, the tree we
were under, and this tree, and these caves, it's clear. What
is the reason for the presence of mulberries here?
English Translation
هل استفاد منه سكان القرية سابقاً؟
Did the village residents benefit from it in the past?
English Translation
نعم، وأنا سألت من كبار السن من عمتي، إنه قالت كان بوقتها
عمرها 95، كانت هي صاحية.
English Translation
Yes, and I asked the elders, like my aunt, who was 95 at the
time, she was in good health.
English Translation
قالت يا ابني، قلت لها يا عمتي ليش عم تزرعين كل حوش، هلق ما
في قليل الحوش الشجر التوت، كل حوش فيه شجرة توت.
English Translation
She said, "My son," I told her, "Aunt, why do you plant in
every courtyard? Now there are few courtyards with mulberry
trees, but every courtyard used to have a mulberry tree."
English Translation
قالت يا ابني كان عم بيربوا دود الحرير على الشجرة، على أوراق
التوت.
English Translation
She said, "My son, they used to raise silkworms on the tree,
on the mulberry leaves."
English Translation
بيطعموه لبين ما بيكبر، بيعمل شرنقة، وكان عم بيعملوا حرير
بالبيوت.
English Translation
They would feed them until they grew and made a cocoon, and
they used to make silk in the houses.
English Translation
بالبيوت؟
In the houses?
English Translation
بالبيوت، لكن.
In the houses, of course.
English Translation
هالحكي من زمان؟
Was this a long time ago?
English Translation
إيوا، بالبيوت كان عم بيعملوا.
Yes, they used to do it in the houses.
English Translation
مو للتجارة يعني؟
Not for trade, I mean?
English Translation
لا.
No.
English Translation
بقي سؤالين. مزار الشيخ غريب هنيك؟ مبينة عنا، إيش في هنيك؟
Two questions remain. The shrine of Sheikh Gharib over
there? It's visible to us, what's over there?
English Translation
الشيخ غريب هذا ولي، له مستشهد هون.
Sheikh Gharib is a saint, he was martyred here.
English Translation
أخي، كمان يعني الزيارة اللي، هي القبة اللي عاملينها شي 400
سنة 500 سنة.
English Translation
Brother, also the shrine, this dome they built is around 400
or 500 years old.
English Translation
اللي عمرها اسمها جونو، من عشيرة... عشيرة عيسى.
The one who built it is named Juno, from the tribe... the
Issa tribe.
English Translation
وادي الموت، اللي هون؟ وين صاير؟
Wadi Al-Mawt (Valley of Death), which is here? Where is it
located?
English Translation
وادي الموت صاير بقبلية سنكرلي. صاير بين قطمة وسنكرلي وخربة
شران.
English Translation
Wadi Al-Mawt is south of Sinkaerli. It's located between
Qatma, Sinkaerli, and Kharbat Sharran.
English Translation
تابع إلكن؟
Does it belong to you?
English Translation
تابع، لا صاير بالنص يعني. أكثر شي تابع لقطمة.
Belong, no, it's in the middle. Mostly it belongs to Qatma.
English Translation
ليش سموه وادي الموت؟
Why did they call it the Valley of Death?
English Translation
وادي الموت، هاد صار يعني، صار صراع ما بين رعاة تبع المنطقة،
ورعاة اللي كان بيجوا من سهل إعزاز.
English Translation
Wadi Al-Mawt, this happened, I mean, a conflict happened
between the shepherds of the area, and the shepherds who
used to come from the Azaz plain.
English Translation
بيجيبوا المعز والشغلات. عم بيقولوا ما شفنا...
They would bring goats and stuff. They say we haven't
seen...
English Translation
صراع ع المي؟
A conflict over water?
English Translation
إي ع المي، إنه كان في تلات آبار. أنا سمعت من الختيارية، ماني
شايفهم.
English Translation
Yes, over the water, that there were three wells. I heard
from the elders, I haven't seen them.
English Translation
إنه كان في بهالوادي هاد تلات آبار مي، هلق ضايعين ما في.
That there used to be three water wells in this valley, now
they are lost, they don't exist.
English Translation
هنيك صاير قتال بينه، وملقبين هداك الوادي، لل، صار في موتى...
A fight happened there between them, and they nicknamed that
valley... because there were deaths...
English Translation
إيوا كلي كوستيا، وادي القتلى، وادي قتيل، وادي قتيل. يعني
واحد بزمانه قايل بتجيني بتشوفني بوادي قتيل، هاد معناتها قايل
بده يقتلني. ما بيعرف اسم الوادي وادي قتيل.
English Translation
Yes, Geliyê Kuştiya (Valley of the Killed), Valley of the
Killed, Wadi Qateel, Wadi Qateel. I mean, back in the day,
someone said "Come see me in Wadi Qateel," which meant he
intended to kill him. He didn't know the name of the valley
was Wadi Qateel.
English Translation
هاد اللي بيعكس سر يعني إنه الناس هون بالأصل كانوا غنامة، أجو
لهون بحثاً عن الماء والكلاء لحيواناتهم.
English Translation
This reflects a secret, meaning that the people here were
originally sheep herders, they came here searching for water
and pasture for their animals.
English Translation
صح، أولي كانوا هيك، وتوطنوا هون، وتوطنوا بهالمغر هي.
True, in the past they were like that, and they settled
here, and they settled in these caves.
English Translation
هي المغارات، هي واحد، اتنين، تلاتة، أربعة، وهنيك أربعة،
تمانة، بهالطرف الوادي...
English Translation
These caves, here's one, two, three, four, and over there
four, eight, on this side of the valley...
English Translation
وعلى أطراف الوادي.
And on the edges of the valley.
English Translation
إيوا، أنا شفت كان عم بيحطوا دوابهم يعني.
Yes, I saw them putting their livestock there.
English Translation
قبل ما بيبدأ، بيكتر الحجر والكمبريسات والشغلات وبيتون،
العالم كان بحاجة كان عم بيستعملها.
English Translation
Before it began, before stones, compressors, and concrete
became abundant, people needed them and used them.
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو دشتي.
May God give you health, Uncle Abu Dashti.
English Translation
على راسي أهلاً وسهلاً.
You're welcome, glad to have you.
English Translation
شكراً إلك.
Thank you.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً أهلين بشباب، تحياتي لكم.
Welcome, welcome guys, my greetings to you.
English Translation
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
English Translation
المرأة في سنكرلي هي دينامو الحياة، لا بل إنها سر الحياة في
هذه القرية البسيطة الجميلة.
English Translation
The woman in Sinkaerli is the dynamo of life; rather, she is
the secret of life in this simple and beautiful village.
English Translation
هي شريكة الرجل في كل شيء، في الفرح، وفي الترح، في المعاناة،
وفي العيش، وفي العمل، وفي الدراسة.
English Translation
She is the man's partner in everything: in joy, in sorrow,
in suffering, in living, in work, and in education.
English Translation
لنتعرف على أوضاع المرأة في سنكرلي، سنزور السيدة مشي رزاد
لتعطينا لمحة عن أوضاع المرأة في هذه القرية الجميلة. تابعونا.
English Translation
To learn about the situation of women in Sinkaerli, we will
visit Mrs. Mshirzad to give us a glimpse of the situation of
women in this beautiful village. Stay with us.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
English Translation
مرحبا عمو.
Hello, uncle.
English Translation
أهلين.
Welcome.
English Translation
شلونك؟
How are you?
English Translation
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
English Translation
ماما موجودة؟
Is mom here?
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
English Translation
يا رب، تسمحي لنا ندخل؟
O Lord, will you allow us to enter?
English Translation
تفضلوا، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Come in, welcome.
English Translation
يا رب.
O Lord.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
وعليكم السلام، أهلاً وسهلاً.
And upon you be peace, welcome.
English Translation
مرحبا عمو. شلونك؟
Hello, uncle. How are you?
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل.
Welcome, come in.
English Translation
مرحبا مشي رزاد.
Hello, Mshirzad.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
English Translation
خيي ابركوا هون، ابركوا، شرفي.
Brother, sit down here, sit down, please.
English Translation
ارتاحي. شلونك؟
Relax. How are you?
English Translation
الحمد لله، شلونك أنت؟
Thank God, how are you?
English Translation
الله يخليكي. شو أخباركم؟
May God keep you. How are you all doing?
English Translation
والله الحمد لله.
By God, thank God.
English Translation
شرفي، اقعدي.
Please, take a seat.
English Translation
شرفي. خلينا نتعرف عليكم أنتو. ولادك مو هيك؟
Please. Let's get to know you. These are your children,
right?
English Translation
إي الحمد لله.
Yes, thank God.
English Translation
شو عندك ولاد مشي رزاد؟
How many children do you have, Mshirzad?
English Translation
صبيين وبنتين.
Two boys and two girls.
English Translation
الله يخليهم، شو أسماءهم؟
May God protect them, what are their names?
English Translation
شيرزاد، جانيار، ليان، روسلين.
Sherzad, Janyar, Liyan, Roslin.
English Translation
جانيار.
Janyar.
English Translation
جانيار. الصبية الحلوة؟
Janyar. And the beautiful young lady?
English Translation
روسلين.
Roslin.
English Translation
وهون؟
And here?
English Translation
ليان.
Liyan.
English Translation
شو معناه روسلين؟
What does Roslin mean?
English Translation
الشمس عند المغيب.
The sun at sunset.
English Translation
يا سلام، يا سلام. وليان؟
Oh wow, wow. And Liyan?
English Translation
ليان المعشوقة.
Liyan means the beloved.
English Translation
المعشوقة. يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
The beloved. Welcome indeed.
English Translation
هنن ليان نحن بالكردي بنقول لها ليون.
Liyan, we pronounce it as "Liyon" in Kurdish.
English Translation
هيك اللهجة.
That's the dialect.
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
على فكرة لهجتكم بسنكرلي متميزة شي عن باقي القرى مثلاً عن
شران وكذا، إيش اللي بيميزها؟
English Translation
By the way, your dialect in Sinkaerli is somewhat distinct
from other villages, like Sharran and such. What makes it
distinct?
English Translation
نحن إيش بيقولوا لها؟ هلق في أغلبية إيزيدية كانوا من قبل، هنن
كان لغتهم غير الأكراد اللي باقية.
English Translation
What do they call it? Well, there was a Yazidi majority in
the past, their language was different from the rest of the
Kurds.
English Translation
اللغة ولا اللهجة؟
The language or the dialect?
English Translation
اللهجة، اللهجة.
The dialect, the dialect.
English Translation
يعني مثلاً قاسية؟ بمطوها؟ بتميل شلون؟
Meaning, for example, is it harsh? Do they stretch it? How
does it lean?
English Translation
قاسية وهيك بنطولها شوي.
It's harsh and we drag it out a bit.
English Translation
بتطولوها شوي.
You drag it out a bit.
English Translation
إي، فيها مد.
Yes, it has elongation.
English Translation
طيب خلينا نحكي هلق عن المرأة في سنكرلي. احكي لي هيك عن
المرأة بشكل عام، وضعها، حياتها، معيشتها؟
English Translation
Alright, let's talk now about the woman in Sinkaerli. Tell
me about women in general, their situation, their lives,
their livelihood?
English Translation
هلق هي بتعيش بسيطة، يعني بتقول حالة الأحوال المادية لا، مو
زيادة، بس كل وحدة مقتنعة بعيشتها.
English Translation
Well, she lives simply. I mean, regarding the financial
situation, it's not much, but everyone is content with their
life.
English Translation
بتروح مع جوزها بتساعده بالشغل، بتيجي بتساعد ولادها إذا عم
يدرسوا بتساعدهم بالدراسة، وبتشتغل شغل البيت، الطبخ وهيك، هاي
هي.
English Translation
She goes with her husband and helps him at work, comes back
and helps her children with their studies if they are
studying, and does the housework, cooking, and so on. That's
it.
English Translation
في شي بيميز حياتها، يعني اليوم المرأة مثلاً في سنكرلي ناضلت
لحتى تاخد حقوقها وتصير متساوية مع الرجل، ولا بالأصل طبيعة
المجتمع أعطتها هالحق؟
English Translation
Is there something that distinguishes her life? I mean,
today, did the woman in Sinkaerli, for example, struggle to
get her rights and become equal to the man, or did the
nature of the society originally grant her this right?
English Translation
والله لا، بالأول لا، ناضلت كتير لبين ما أخدوا هالحق.
By God, no, at first no. They struggled a lot until they got
this right.
English Translation
كيف؟ احكي لي.
How? Tell me.
English Translation
يعني الأغلبية ما كانوا يبعتوا بناتهم ع المدرسة. ما كانوا
يخلوا البنات يدرسوا.
English Translation
I mean, the majority wouldn't send their daughters to
school. They wouldn't let the girls study.
English Translation
بعدين بعد شوي بعد فترة، صاروا يروحوا يدرسوا، ودخلوا ع
الجامعات، هلق في نسبة منيحة هلق درسوا.
English Translation
Then, little by little, after a while, they started going to
study, and entered universities. Now there's a good
percentage who have studied.
English Translation
إيش درسوا عندكم؟ إيش عندكم شهادات؟
What did they study here? What degrees do you have?
English Translation
في شهادات دكاترة والله، بنات وصبيان، درسوا دكاترة، صيادلة،
مهندسين، في آنسات مدرسة، أساتذة. يعني في نسبة منيحة.
English Translation
There are doctorate degrees, by God, girls and boys. They
studied to be doctors, pharmacists, engineers. There are
school teachers, professors. I mean, there's a good
percentage.
English Translation
يعني إنتي بتشوفي اليوم إنه المجتمع أصبح يعني مساعد، لأنه
المرأة تقوم بدور إيجابي كبير، وهي سر الحياة هون.
English Translation
So you see today that the society has become, you know,
supportive, for the woman to play a large positive role, and
she is the secret of life here.
English Translation
إي والله، بيساعدوا.
Yes, by God, they help.
English Translation
بيساعدوا وصاروا يتعاونوا، وصارت المرأة هون مثقفة أكتر.
They help and have started cooperating, and the woman here
has become more educated.
English Translation
وحتى يعني مثلاً تروح ع المدرسة تيجي ع البيت توعي أهلها كمان.
إلها دور توعي أمها.
English Translation
And even, for example, she goes to school, comes home, and
educates her family as well. She has a role in educating her
mother.
Heta l-mera el-ummiyye, bes sarit titalem min wladha kaman.
Even the uneducated woman, she started learning from her
children as well.
Yanî ixtilafit el-mefahîm el-ictima'iyye 'an ewwelî..
Meaning, the social concepts have differed from before...
Fîma yexuss el-mer'e.
Yes, of course.
Regarding women.
Esbah fî teqebbul la-'emele, w la-dore l-ictima'î, w
wezîfete.
Yes.
Esbah fî teqebbul la-'emele, w la-dore l-ictima'î, w
wezîfete.
There is now an acceptance of her work, her social role, and
her job.
Ê, min qebil ma kano yxellu l-mer'e truh tiştixil titwezzef
aw şî,
Yes, before they wouldn't let women go out to work or get a
job or anything,
Heta law taxud haş-şehade bes hella, bi-has-senewat la',
sar..
Even if she got a degree, but now, in these years no, it
became...
Hella ay met sar hat-texyîr had?
When exactly did this change happen?
Yanî e-qell şî sar şî xamsa w işrîn sine.
At least about twenty-five years ago.
Xamsa w işrîn sine..
Twenty-five years...
Ê.
Yes.
Qebil ha la' ma kan fî wella..
Before that no there wasn't, or...
Yimkin min xamsa w işrîn sine, heta Senkerlî yanî
tetawwerit...
Maybe since twenty-five years, even Senkerli has
developed...
Kanit qerye zxîre besîte, esbahit yanî mutemeddine ekter.
It was a small, simple village, it became more urbanized.
Ê lekan. Sarit mutetawwire ekter.
Yes, of course. It became more developed.
Bi-sebeb yanî me'îşit qisim kbîr min sukkanha bi-Heleb.
Due to a large part of its population living in Aleppo.
Bi-Heleb.. nizlu 'a Heleb.. nizlu 'a 'Efrîn. Medîne, mû
mitil qerye.. ma fîha şixil.
In Aleppo... they moved down to Aleppo... they moved down to
Afrin. A city, not like a village... there is no work here.
Teyyib, hada t-tetawwur llî sar bi-wed' el-mer'e wel-mefahîm
el-ictima'iyye, sar fî aydan texyîr şî biz-ziyy er-resmî
lil-mer'e?
Okay, this development that happened in the status of women
and social concepts, did there also happen any change in the
traditional dress of women?
Ê lekan.
Yes, of course.
Sar min qebil kinna nilbis meselen fistan Kurdî, le kişkiş
min taht w hîk, w xîşab w.. bes hella..
How?
Sar min qebil kinna nilbis meselen fistan Kurdî, le kişkiş
min taht w hîk, w xîşab w.. bes hella..
Before we used to wear, for example, a Kurdish dress, with
frills at the bottom and so on, and a headscarf... but
now...
Ba'd ma saru bil-medaris w yitla'u w yifutu ma 'adu yilbisu,
After they started going to schools and going out, they
stopped wearing it,
Banatîl, bilwize 'adiyye, fî minhum byithajjabu, fî minhum
ma byithajjabu.
Trousers, a regular blouse, some of them wear a hijab, some
don't.
Yanî saru jizi' min t-tekwin el-'am, ma lun xususiyye.
Meaning they became a part of the general makeup, they don't
have a specific distinction.
Ma lun xususiyye, la'.
They don't have a specific distinction, no.
Temam. Hella şo 'am titbixî intî? Şo 'adek tsawwî?
Okay. Now, what are you cooking? What are you making?
'Am itbux boraniyye.
I am cooking Boraniyya.
Boraniyye?
Boraniyya?
Yanî l-boraniyye min êş m'ellefe?
Yes.
What is Boraniyya made of?
'Adas, hummos, bîncan, kûsa, w zêt, w leben.
Lentils, chickpeas, eggplants, zucchinis, oil, and yogurt.
Ehem şî l-leben. Leben el-xenem hella weqto.
The most important thing is the yogurt. Sheep yogurt, now is
its season.
Hella heydi kem mukewwin ila, seb'a hasab ma smi'it, seb'a?
Now, how many ingredients does this have, seven from what I
heard, seven?
Ê.
Yes.
Hiyyi nefsa bsemmuha seb'a duwel?
Is it the same one they call Seven Countries?
La' nahnî hon la', msemmîha Boraniyye nahnî.
No, us here no, we call it Boraniyya.
Kîf btitbuxuha?
How do you cook it?
Hella mnisluq el-'adas wel-hummos lahala 'a teref.
Now we boil the lentils and chickpeas separately on the
side.
W ba'dên mnjîb el-basal mnhutto fawq ez-zêt mnqellî,
And then we get the onions, put them in the oil and fry
them,
W mnhut me'o benadora w bîncan w kûsa, iza biddo... hasab..
kil wahid w şlon ma bihib..
And we put tomatoes, eggplants, and zucchinis with it, if
they want... it depends... however each person likes it...
W ba'd ma nxallis, mndewwir el-leben.. ba'd ma ndewwir el-
leben, mnhut kilha me' ba'don, w mnixlîha.
And after we finish, we stir the yogurt... after we stir the
yogurt, we put them all together and boil them.
W sihtên w hana.
Bon appétit.
'A qelbak, ehla w sehlan.
Bless you, welcome.
Şo byintikel canba?
What is eaten with it?
La' nahnî mnakla hîk.
No, we eat it just like this.
Ê, lahala feqat.
Just by itself?
Yes, just by itself.
Ma byintikel canba riz, burxul, frîke..?
Rice, bulgur, or freekeh isn't eaten with it?
La' ma mnamil şî.. ebeden. Ê.
No, we don't make anything... at all. Yes.
W hîk betkon yanî.. mreqqa inno muraqqa..
And so it is... brothy, like a stew...
La' ma btitla' maraq.
No, it doesn't turn out like a broth.
W hada weqta?
And this is its season?
Hada weqta. Ê.
This is its season. Yes.
W hayy ekle şa'biyye hon?
And is this a popular dish here?
Ekle şa'biyye w ma'rufe hon 'anna.
It's a popular and well-known dish here with us.
Bi kil mintaqit 'Efrîn wella bes hon?
In the whole Afrin region or just here?
Kil mintaqit 'Efrîn. Linno bes nahnî l-Krad mnamila.
The whole Afrin region. Because only we Kurds make it.
Ya sîdî Allah hîk inşallah yis'idkon.
Oh my sir, may God make you happy.
Teyyib xellînî kaman ahkî ma' el-ayin le'indî..
Alright, let me also talk to the girl here...
Ta'î la hon.
Come here.
La hon la hon...
Here, here...
Intî eyye sef?
What grade are you in?
Rabi'.
Fourth.
Rabi'. Ekîd intî muctehide ekter min Canyar.
Fourth. You are definitely more hardworking than Janyar.
Mm.
Axadtu cela'at?
Did you get your report cards?
La' lissa.
No, not yet.
La-êmet?
Until when?
Lil-xamîs.
Until Thursday.
Êmet txallisu fahs?
When do you finish exams?
Hella.
Just now.
L-yom yanî.
Meaning today.
Kan axir fahs l-yom.
Today was the last exam.
Intî 'am darrisik ustad wella anse?
Are you being taught by a male teacher or a female teacher?
Anse.
A female teacher.
Anse. Kwayyis.
A female teacher. Good.
Şo rah tsîrî intî şo bidik tiştixlî inşallah bil-musteqbal?
What will you become? What do you want to work as in the
future, God willing?
Muhendise.
An engineer.
Muhendise êş?
An engineer of what?
Kumbyuter.
Computer.
Maşallah 'alêkî, ma'nata bthibbî l-kumbyuter wel-mobayl w
heş-şaxlat, şatre mu hîk?
Mashallah to you, that means you love computers, mobiles,
and these things. You're smart, aren't you?
Roho qelbo.
It is my heart and soul.
Roh w qelbo.
Her heart and soul.
Şo l-sebeb lîş bidik tsîrî muhendise kumbyuter?
What is the reason, why do you want to become a computer
engineer?
Habbêto.
I liked it.
Kint 'am şofo hîk.. kil yom şofo.. habbêt heş-şixle.
I used to see it like this... see it every day... I liked
this job.
Yallah Allah yqewwîkî ya rabb,
Well, may God give you strength, oh Lord,
W inşallah btsîrî bil-musteqbal ş-şî llî btrîdî w ahsen
kaman,
And God willing, you'll become what you want in the future,
and even better,
W nşofik yanî 'alime bi-hendeset l-kumbyuterat.
And we will see you as a scholar in computer engineering.
Tislem.
Thanks.
Şukran ya Canyar.
Thank you, Janyar.
Allah yi'tîkon el-'afiye. Mşî ya zed.
May God give you health. Let's go.
Allah y'afîk, ehlan w sehlan fîkom, ehla w sehlan.
May God give you health, welcome to you, welcome.
El-byut fî Senkerlî tehmil şexsiyyet el-qerye,
The houses in Senkerli carry the village's character,
W tumessil tabî'et ehliha, el-cebeliyye, es-sa'be.
And represent the tough, mountainous nature of its people.
Nemet el-bina' fî hazihi l-qerye yetemaha temaman ma' el-
cuxrafya el-heqîqiyye li-hazihi l-qerye.
The architectural style in this village perfectly blends
with the true geography of this village.
Senakon me'akum fî hazihi l-feqre fî ziyare li-ehad byut el-
qerye,
We will be with you in this segment, visiting one of the
village houses,
El-'amm Ebu Muhammed, ledeyhi beyt qedîm, 'umruhu yetecawwez
el-mi'et 'am.
Uncle Abu Muhammad has an old house over a hundred years
old.
Senequm bi-ziyaretihi min ecli t-te'erruf 'ala nemeti
l-bina' fî Senkerlî. Tabi'una.
We will visit him to learn about the architectural style in
Senkerli. Follow us.
Ebu Muhammed!
Abu Muhammad!
Tefeddelu.
Come in.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Wa aleykum es-selam wa rahmetullah wa berekatuh.
And peace be upon you, and the mercy of Allah and His
blessings.
Şlonak?
How are you?
Ya ehla w sehlen bi-şebab, tefeddelu.
Oh, welcome guys, come in.
Ya rabb...
Oh Lord...
Es-selamu aleykum Ebu Muhammed.
Peace be upon you, Abu Muhammad.
Aleykum es-selam wa rahmetullah wa berekatuh. Ya hala, ahlen
w sehlen ya axuy.
And peace be upon you, and the mercy of Allah and His
blessings. Oh welcome, welcome my brother.
Şlon sihhtak?
How is your health?
El-hamdulillah, kîfkon inton?
Thank God, how are you?
Xellîna nîcî la-hon şway.
Let's come here a little bit.
Tefeddel.
Go ahead.
Sahib el-beyt hedirtak?
Are you the owner of the house?
Ene, sahib min hon el-beyt el-Hec Mustafa.
I am, the owner of the house is Hajj Mustafa.
Hada l-beyt el-Hec Mustafa.
This is Hajj Mustafa's house.
Eywa.
Yes.
Ene ibno. Huwwe mtweffî.
And you are his son?
I am his son. He passed away.
Beqa b-'umro w 'umrak.
May he rest in peace.
Allah yirhamo.
May God have mercy on him.
Sîdî, şqed 'imru hal-beyt? Xellîna nwakkif hon şway, nicî
la-hon şan nşuf el-beyt.
Sir, how old is this house? Let's stand here a bit, come
over here so we can see the house.
Wallah 'umro hon hewalî şî mîyye w 'işrîn, mîyye w tlathîn
sine.
Honestly, it's about a hundred and twenty, a hundred and
thirty years old here.
Mîyye w 'işrîn, mîyye w tlathîn sine. Hella hada wadêh el-
hacer qedîm ktîr.
A hundred and twenty, a hundred and thirty years. Now it is
clear that the stone is very old.
Qedîm eywa, kem beyt qedîme.
Yes, it is old, it's an old house.
Mneyn cibtu hacaru had?
Where did you get this stone from?
Hay hecer kan Allah yirham ciddî, kan cabo min el-col,
This stone, may God have mercy on my grandfather, he brought
it from the wilderness,
Cabo m'essawayy taht, 'ammarto.
He brought it, leveled it down there, and built it.
Şlon şekil el-beyt, hada eqdem beyt bed-day'a?
What's the shape of the house, is this the oldest house in
the village?
Hay, aqdem beyt bed-day'a..
Yes, this is an old house in the village...
Bes mo aqdem beyt fî d-day'a.
But not the oldest house in the village.
Eywa.
Yes.
Teyyib farcînî l-xurfe.. wahde min l-xuraf.
Okay, show me the room... one of the rooms.
Tefeddel.
Go ahead.
Hella l-beyt qismên, el-qaws qasmo qismên. Daxelî w berranî.
Now the house is two sections, the arch divides it into two
sections. Inner and outer.
Cuwwanî w berranî.
Inner and outer.
Ya aynî aleyk. W hada l-qaws. Smîk ktîr.
Exactly. And this is the arch. It is very thick.
Lakan, hada kellîn.
Of course, this is solid.
Hon êş hattîn hon?
What did they put here?
Kano hattîn hon xzane mitil hnita, mitil ş'îr, hay kile
mûne, mûne.
They used to put a cupboard here, like for wheat, like for
barley, this is all for provisions, provisions.
W is-seqif, şqed 'imro had?
And the ceiling, how old is it?
Imro hay keman min mîyye w tlathîn mîyye w erba'în sene.
It is also a hundred and thirty, a hundred and forty years
old.
S-seqif nefso yanî ma tcedded?
Meaning the ceiling itself wasn't renewed?
La'. Xeşeb w s-smo, qiş, tebe' s-smo.
No. Wood and smoothness, straw, of the smoothness.
Qiş. W haydi.. middade?
Straw. And this... a rug?
Haydi middade, hay zra'at hîk meselen menzer.
This is a rug, these are crops like a decoration for
example.
Menzer. Ya selam. Ktîr el-beyt hîk şî ktîr hilo.
Decoration. Oh wow. The house is very, very beautiful.
Hada middat l-.. besat hada.
This is a rug... a carpet.
Hay maddat l-qedîme hayde teba' el-kan awwaliyye hazol am
yisawwuhon.
This is an old rug from the old days, they used to make
these.
Hon şuxl ed-day'a?
Village work here?
W hîk kaman hnîk, hay kaman is-sicon hon.
Yes, village work.
And like that over there too, this is also a mat here.
Ewa. Hada nafs ş-şî. Kan Allah yirhamha kan nentî am
tisawwîhon mitil el-... nis l-hoş.. w tisawwiha.
Yes. This is the same thing. May God have mercy on her, my
grandmother used to make them like the... in the middle of
the courtyard... and she would make it.
Ya selam, w hazol killon hîk nafs ş-şî hon.
Wow, and all these are the same thing here.
Hazol keman... bes hazol el-qedîmiyye.
These too... but these are the old ones.
Xellîna nitla' la-berra. Nşuf.
Let's go outside. Let's see.
Hella el-beyt fî cibb mayy.
Now the house has a water well.
Fî cibb mayy kaman. Ne'am.
It has a water well too. Yes.
Xellîna nşofo.
Let's see it.
Yallah tefeddelu.
Alright, go ahead.
Ya rabb.
Oh Lord.
Hay el-cibb.
Here's the well.
Hada qedîm, aqdem mil-beyt wella ma' l-beyt?
Is this old, older than the house or with the house?
La' hay kan 'amaret el-beyt, w sawwet el-cibb. Eywa.
No, this was built when the house was built, and the well
was made. Yes.
W xamqoh seba' imtar, seba' imtar w nuss.
And its depth is seven meters, seven and a half meters.
Hada cem' wella nebi'?
Is this a collector or a spring?
La' hada cem'. Mayy meter w bi-şite bi'abbu.
No, this is a collector. Rainwater, and in the winter it
fills up.
Tayyib. Êş haş-şecere hiye?
Okay. What is this tree?
Hay şecret el.. kebbad, yanî kebbad.
This is a citron tree, meaning citron.
Eywa. Hay ktîr hilwe ha-z-zira'at llî 'andkon ktîr cemîle,
I see. This is very beautiful, these plants you have are
very beautiful,
Wa l-birke, kil anwa'a maşallah l-wrud w z-zuhur.
And the pond, all kinds of roses and flowers, mashallah.
Eş-şecer llî hon... Sma'it inno hon fî 'ankon êş fî tahit
l-beyt hon?
The trees here... I heard that you have, what is under the
house here?
Tefeddel.
Go ahead.
Hay kanet mikan ma'sara.
This was a place for a press.
Hon kan fî ma'sara? Ê kan fî ma'sara.
There was a press here? Yes, there was a press here.
Eywa. M'anata fî qabu hon?
I see. That means there is a basement here?
Ê qabu. Qabu w ma'sara. Ma'sara qedîme.
Yes, a basement. A basement and a press. An old press.
Hella şo.. xellset el-ma'sara, hon şo hon?
Now what... the press is gone, what is here?
Hon maxara. Kan dawwab w xanamat w tibnat w killo 'am
yihuttu hon.
Here is a cave. There were animals, sheep, hay, and they
used to put everything here.
Alowwal kaman t'axuda. Ktîr hilwe.
The first ones took it too. Very beautiful.
Kbîre hay. Wasa' kbîre.
This is big. Broadly big.
Xellîna nitla'.
Let's go out.
Tefeddel.
Go ahead.
Hattîn monet et-tom b-qelb ş-şecera.
They put the garlic provisions in the heart of the tree.
Eywa, tom hada taht minşan mûne. Eywa.
Yes, this garlic is underneath for provisions. Yes.
Ktîr hilwe. Ktîr hilo. Hella hon şo fî hon metbax hon?
Very beautiful. Very nice. Now what is here, a kitchen?
Ê hay metbax.
Yes, this is a kitchen.
Tefeddel.
Go ahead.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Wa aleykum es-selam w rahmetullah w berekatuh.
And peace be upon you, and the mercy of Allah and His
blessings.
Allah yi'tîki l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
Şo 'am titbuxî l-yom?
What are you cooking today?
Wallah 'am nitbux burxul b-benadora.
Well, we are cooking bulgur with tomatoes.
Ya ehlên w sehlên.
Oh, double welcome.
Allah yi'tîkon el-'afiye.
May God keep you safe.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk ehla w sehlan.
May God give you health, welcome.
El-burxul b-benadora hay ekle şa'biyye hon.
Bulgur with tomatoes is a popular dish here.
Ê ekle şa'biyye hon, burxul b-benadora. Ê.
Yes, it's a popular dish here, bulgur with tomatoes. Yes.
Hada şo had? Hada l-narinj?
What is this? Is this bitter orange?
La' hada şo ismo.. liz-zburat yanî. Xitmiyye.
No, what is it called... it's for decoration. Hollyhock.
Allah yi'tîki l-'afiye. Nşallah sahtên w hana.
May God give you health. Hopefully bon appétit.
Ala qelbak. Allah y'afîk. Ehla w sehlan.
Bless you. May God give you health. Welcome.
Ya rabb. Allah yi'tîk el-'afiye Ebu Muhammed.
Oh Lord. May God give you health, Abu Muhammad.
Ahla w sehlen.
Welcome.
Allah ysallmak şukran ilkun.
May God keep you safe, thank you to you all.
B-hal-feqre l-axîre min el-cewle, rah nt'erraf 'ala şexsiyye
mumeyyeze ktîr b-Senkerlî.
In this last segment of the tour, we will get to know a very
distinct personality in Senkerli.
Ebu 'Elî, şexsiyye bthibb ktîr turas, w bthibb el-antîka, w
kil şî qedîm,
Abu Ali, a personality who really loves heritage, and loves
antiques, and everything old,
W şexsiyye eydan bti'timid 'ala zata. Bêto eydan mumeyyez
bi-tertîbo.
And also a personality who relies on himself. His house is
also distinct in its arrangement.
Rah niduxol ma'kum 'ala beyt Ebu 'Elî la-nt'erraf 'alê, w
'ala l-eşya' ellî bihibba. Tabi'una.
We will enter Abu Ali's house with you to get to know him,
and the things he loves. Follow us.
Ebu 'Elî!
Abu Ali!
Yallah, yallah!
Coming, coming!
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum es-selam. Ya ahlen wa sehlen ahlen.
And peace be upon you. Oh welcome, welcome.
Şlonak Ebu 'Elî?
How are you, Abu Ali?
'Ala rasî ahla w sehlan. Tefeddelu, tefeddelu ahla w sehlan
biş-şebab, ya hala.
Upon my head, welcome. Come in, come in, welcome guys, oh
welcome.
Tefeddelu, ahla w sehlan.
Come in, welcome.
Ahlen Ebu Ali.
Welcome, Abu Ali.
Ya hala, ahlen.
Oh welcome, welcome.
Hada beytak?
Is this your house?
Maşallah 'alêk, beytak mezra'a ktîr... lifet nezerî ebel şî
l-kelb. Şo had l-kelb?
Yes, by God.
Maşallah 'alêk, beytak mezra'a ktîr... lifet nezerî ebel şî
l-kelb. Şo had l-kelb?
Mashallah to you, your house is very much a farm... what
caught my eye first is the dog. What is this dog?
Hada fîno biqulolo. Fîno şî sxîr, hada hirase yanî mitl
ceras,
This they call it a Fino. Fino is something small, this is
for guarding, like a bell,
Iza wahid yiduqq el-bab şî 'arfan kîf? Bi'awwî, ke-inno
ceras.. 'awwad ceras hawîno l-hada, ê. Saffaret inzar.
If someone knocks on the door or something, you know? It
barks, as if it's a bell... instead of a bell, this holds
it, yes. A siren.
Saffaret inzar. Beyt hilo ktîr maşallah. 'Andak inno
heywanat keman?
A siren. A very beautiful house, mashallah. You have animals
too?
Ê wallah anzat 'andî l-hamdulillah.
Yes, by God, I have goats, thank God.
Hazol yanî, l-ma'iz, lit-terbiye lil-halîb wella êş hazol?
These goats, are they for breeding, for milk, or what are
these for?
Wallah lil-halîb.. 'am nistifad minno. 'Arfan kîf, 'am
nihlibon, nsawwî fîyo jibne... w...
Honestly for milk... we benefit from them. You know, we milk
them, we make cheese from it... and...
Êş l-anzat llî 'andak?
What goats do you have?
هاد بيقولوا عليه عجمي، يعني قريب ع الشامي.
They call this Ajami, meaning it's close to Shami.
في تلات أنواع، في عادي وفي عجمي وفي شامي.
There are three types: normal, Ajami, and Shami.
هاد مو شامي، عجمي.
This is not Shami, it's Ajami.
عجمي ايش بيميزه عن الشامي وعن العادي؟
Ajami, what distinguishes it from Shami and the normal one?
هلا الشامي بيكون منقاره بيكون أكبر من هيك، عرفان كيف؟ وتمه
شوي لقدام.
Well, the Shami has a bigger beak than this, you know? And
its mouth is a bit forward.
هاد نسبة عجمي بيشبهه يعني، بيكون تيس شامي، يعني بيجي سخلات
كمان شاميين.
This has an Ajami percentage, it resembles it. It would be a
Shami billy goat, meaning the young goats also come out
Shami.
ندخل شوي لهون.
Let's go in a bit here.
حديقة كتير حلوة ما شاء الله، دوالي، كرمة...
A very beautiful garden, Mashallah, grapevines, vineyards...
الحمد لله خضار يعني، الضيعة هي خضار حلوة، عرفان كيف؟
Thank God, there's greenery. The village has beautiful
greenery, you know?
واحد هيك بيتضمن الضيعة، مو متل المدينة، الضيعة بدو يكون عنده
جاج، بدو يكون عنده غنم، بدو يكون عنده كل شي، مخصصين.
One includes these in the village, it's not like the city.
In the village, one needs to have chickens, sheep, and
everything, it's specific.
طيب هي لي هون شو هي؟
Well, what is this one here?
هي شجرة برتقان.
This is an orange tree.
ايش زارع هون؟
What have you planted here?
والله زارعين هون بقدونس لسا مو طالع.
Well, we planted parsley here, it hasn't grown yet.
لهلأ موسمه. وهاد جرجير، الأخضر جرجير.
It's just its season. And this is arugula, the green one is
arugula.
وهاد كمان عرفان كيف؟ أنواع سلق يعني.
And this too, you know? Types of chard.
طيب. السلام عليكم.
Okay. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، مية أهلا وسهلا.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you, a hundred
welcomes.
يعطيك العافية عمي أبو آزاد.
May God give you health, uncle Abu Azad.
يا أهلا وسهلا، بعمي أبو آزاد أهلا وسهلا.
A warm welcome, to my uncle Abu Azad, welcome.
شلونك سيدي؟
How are you, sir?
تفضل.
Please, come in.
نبرك شوي؟
Shall we sit a bit?
يا أهلا وسهلا.
You are very welcome.
احكيلي على اللباس اللي لابسه إنت.
Tell me about the clothes you are wearing.
باعتبارك يعني لابس الآن الزي التقليدي لأهل سنكرلي، هذا هو
اللباس؟
Since you are now wearing the traditional outfit of the
people of Sinkerli, is this the one?
والله هاد مو لأهل سنكرلي، هي بشكل عام لأهل مين كردي كانوا
يلبسوا هيك، لباس كردي.
Well, this is not just for the people of Sinkerli, this is
generally for all Kurds, they used to wear this, it's
Kurdish clothing.
بالأعراس يلبسوا هيك، بالحفل يلبسوا هيك.
At weddings they wear this, at parties they wear this.
حتى بعملهم يعني، عرفان كيف؟ هذا لباسهم، كان أولي ما في يعني
غير هاللبس كان ما في.
Even in their work, you know? This is their clothing, in the
past there was nothing but this clothing.
سروال وطاسومة هي بيقولولها نحن عنا، عرفان كيف؟ وهي بدريسية
وهاد القميص.
Shalwar and this Tasouma as we call it here, you know? And
this is the Badrisiyya (jacket) and this is the shirt.
واللي على راسك؟
And what's on your head?
على راسي هي الطاقية كأن شغل ضيعة عرفان كيف؟ على طول نحن
بالشول وبالبرية.
On my head is this hat, as village work requires, you know?
We are always in the fields and the wilderness.
مشان شو؟ حرارة الشمس. ليش هي عالية هيك؟ مشان حرارة الشمس ما
تضرب ع الراس.
For what? The heat of the sun. Why is it high like this? So
the heat of the sun doesn't hit the head.
بيحمي الراس يعني، متل مظلة.
It protects the head, like an umbrella.
متل مظلة، بس هلق قليل قليل بشوف منها بهالشكل الطويل.
Like an umbrella, but nowadays I rarely see ones in this
tall shape.
أولي كان على طول هيك لبسهم، بس هلق اتطلعوا ع أهل المدن.
In the past, this was always their clothing, but now they
looked at the city people.
شافوا أهل المدن يعني طواقي بيحطوا، أو سلك لحال، ما تم
هالموديل يعني، أولي كان هيك.
They saw city people wearing caps, or just a keffiyeh, this
style doesn't exist anymore. It used to be like this in the
past.
الطاسومة هلق في منها؟ ولا من وين جبتها؟
Are Tasoumas still available? Or where did you get them
from?
والله هي بيلتقى، بيلتقى منها، بس هلق صايرين شو عم يلبسوا؟
خفافات، صبابيط هالشغلات.
Well, you can find them, they can be found, but nowadays
what are they wearing? Light shoes, boots, and such things.
إيش بيميز الطاسومة عن الحذاء العادي عن الخفافة عن الصباط، شو
بيميزها؟
What distinguishes the Tasouma from normal shoes, light
shoes, or boots? What makes it special?
نحن هاللباس بيميز إنه تقاليدنا تقاليد أكراد.
For us, this clothing distinguishes that our traditions are
Kurdish traditions.
يعني هلق أنا وين ما أروح، فرضا ع حلب، ع عفرين، بيعرفوني من
لباسي بيعرفوني كردي.
Meaning now, wherever I go, for example to Aleppo, or Afrin,
they know me by my clothes, they know I'm Kurdish.
بس البس عادي، ما حدا بيميزني إنه أنا كردي لكن من وين أنا ما
بيعرفوني.
But if I dress normally, no one distinguishes me as Kurdish,
they wouldn't know where I'm from.
بس هاللباس بيعرفوني إني كردي، أروح ع الشام أروح ع حلب وين ما
أروح، خلص هاد كردي جاي من بعيد بيعرفوه.
But with this clothing they know I'm Kurdish. Whether I go
to Damascus, to Aleppo, wherever I go, that's it, this is a
Kurd coming from far away, they know it.
الطاسومة كردية؟
Is the Tasouma Kurdish?
طاسومة مو كردية... صناعة، كان أولي يلبسوها، أكراد يلبسوها.
Tasouma is not Kurdish... it's an industry. In the past they
used to wear it, Kurds used to wear it.
يعني بس للأكراد؟ قصدي هي يعني من التراث الكردي ولا سوري ولا
شامي ولا شو؟
You mean only for Kurds? I mean, is it from Kurdish
heritage, or Syrian, or Shami, or what?
لا تراث كردي، كردي وحلبي وشامي، كلهم بيلبسوها أولي.
No, it's Kurdish heritage. Kurdish, Aleppian, and Shami,
everyone used to wear it in the past.
تمام، تمام. خليني أسألك عن الشخصية السنكرلية.
Great, great. Let me ask you about the Sinkerli personality.
ابن سنكرلي بإيش بيتميز؟
What distinguishes someone from Sinkerli?
ابن سنكرلي بيتميز بزراعته، بعمله، بفلاحته، هاد هو ابن
سنكرلي.
The Sinkerli person is distinguished by his farming, his
work, his agriculture, this is the Sinkerli person.
بسيط ولا معقد؟
Simple or complicated?
لا بسيط كتير بسيط، ليش؟ لأنه فلاح هو، الفلاح وين ما يروح
بسيط.
No, simple, very simple. Why? Because he is a farmer. A
farmer is simple wherever he goes.
بس بيفلح بجبال، يعني الطبيعة قاسية وصعبة.
But he farms in the mountains, so the nature is harsh and
difficult.
هي أولي مزبوط هالحكي، أولي كان شو أجدادنا يفلحوا بالسكة
وبالأحصنة.
That was true in the past. In the past, what did our
ancestors use? They plowed with a plowshare and horses.
يعني يطول الكرم معهم نهارين تلاتة هنن عم يفلحوا، نهارين
تلاتة يطول معهم.
The vineyard would take them two or three days to plow. Two
or three days it would take them.
بس صار بعد ما صار تراكتورات، العالم جابت تراكتورات، صارت
سهلة يعني الفلاحة.
But after tractors came, people brought tractors, plowing
became easy.
يعني قصدك، أولي لما كان يتعامل مع المحراث القديم، خلينا
نقول، كان قاسي متل ما كانت الطبيعة قاسية؟
So you mean, in the past when he dealt with the old plow,
let's say, he was harsh just as nature was harsh?
إي، محراث القديم كان صعب الأمور. قاسي مثل ما كانت الطبيعة
قاسية.
Yes, the old plow made things difficult. Harsh just as
nature was harsh.
أما اليوم صار يتماشى مع تطور الحضارة وصار في شوية سهولة
وليونة.
But today he is keeping pace with the development of
civilization and there is a bit of ease and flexibility.
مظبوط، مظبوط، اكيد اكيد مظبوط.
Exactly, exactly. Sure, sure, exactly.
طيب، هلق أنت طالما لابس هيك، معناها بتعرف ترقص كردي.
Well, as long as you are dressed like this, it means you
know how to dance Kurdish dances.
اي والله اكيد لكان، انا كردي وما راح اعرف ارقص كردي ما
بيصير. الكردي بدو يرقص كردي.
Yes, of course. I'm Kurdish and I wouldn't know how to dance
Kurdish? That's impossible. A Kurd must dance Kurdish.
يعني في تلازم بين الشخصية الكردية والرقص؟
So is there a correlation between the Kurdish personality
and dancing?
نفس الشي، الكردي بدو يكون يعرف يرقص، ومو رقصة عنا وحدة،
أنواع في أنواع من الرقص.
It's the same thing, a Kurd must know how to dance, and we
don't have just one dance, there are many types of dances.
احكيلي الأنواع كلها وارقص لي رقصة الرش.
Tell me all the types and dance the Rash dance for me.
في باقية، في حمو، في قرطال بيقولوا له، يعني في أنواع من
الرقص.
There is Baqia, there is Hamo, there is Qartal as they call
it, meaning there are many types of dances.
خاتونية؟
Khatounia?
في خاتونية كمان، شيخانية، الأنواع هدول مظبوط، كتير أنواع.
There is Khatounia too. Sheikhani... these types exactly,
many types.
خلينا نشوفك شو عم ترقص الرش.
Let's see you dance the Rash.
تفضل. في دبكة عربي كمان.
Go ahead. There is an Arabic Dabke too.
لا، مو الرش. دبكة عربي كمان؟
No, not the Rash. An Arabic Dabke too?
في عندنا، في أنواع.
We have it, there are types.
شو راح تسمعنا؟ شو راح ترقص هلق؟
What will you play for us? What are you going to dance now?
هلق بحب أرقص متل ما بدك، يعني حسب الموسيقى هي الرقص بيجي.
Now I'd like to dance whatever you want. I mean, the dance
goes according to the music.
طيب، تفضل.
Alright, go ahead.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
You're very welcome.
[Music]
انتهت جولة هذا الأسبوع والتي قدمناها لكم من قرية سنكرلي في
ريف ناحية شران، منطقة عفرين، ريف حلب الشمالي.
This week's tour, which we presented to you from the village
of Sinkerli in the countryside of Sharran sub-district,
Afrin region, northern Aleppo countryside, has ended.
سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم في جولة جديدة، من قرية سورية
أخرى حبيبة لمتابعة برنامجنا.
We will be with you next week in a new tour, from another
beloved Syrian village, to follow our program.
تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة، وأيضا موقعنا على الانترنت
HalabTodayTV.net.
Follow the channel's Facebook page, and also our website
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
May the peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[Music]